<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon vpon the parable of the King that taketh an accompt of his seruants Math. 18. 23. Wherein is declared, the iustice, mercy, and seueritie of God: the crueltie of man, and his reward for the same. Rising vpon St. Peters question to Christ, viz. How oft shall I forgiue my brother? seauen times? 21. vers. [...]  By Iohn Hoskin, minister of Gods holy word, student in Diuinitie.</title>
            <author>Hoskin, John, minister of Gods holy word.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03713</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13838</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121139</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856326</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856326</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21861</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03713)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21861)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1208:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon vpon the parable of the King that taketh an accompt of his seruants Math. 18. 23. Wherein is declared, the iustice, mercy, and seueritie of God: the crueltie of man, and his reward for the same. Rising vpon St. Peters question to Christ, viz. How oft shall I forgiue my brother? seauen times? 21. vers. [...]  By Iohn Hoskin, minister of Gods holy word, student in Diuinitie.</title>
                  <author>Hoskin, John, minister of Gods holy word.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[60] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. E[ld] for Iohn Wright,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C D⁶.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew XVIII --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21861:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21861:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON vpon the Parable of the King that taketh an accompt <hi>of his ſeruants.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Math. 18.23.</bibl>
               <p>Wherein is declared, the iuſtice, <hi>mercy, and ſeueritie of God: the crueltie</hi> of man, and his reward for the ſame.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Riſing vpon S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</hi> Peters <hi>question to Christ, Viz.</hi> How oft ſhall I forgiue my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? ſeauen times? <bibl>21 verſ.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Fiat voluntari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m, quod futurum est neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarium, &amp; offeramus Deo pro munere, quod pro debito reddere tenemur. <bibl>
                  <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſt. hom. 10. in Mat.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>BY IOHN HOSKIN, Miniſter of Gods holy word, ſtudent in Diuinitie.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed by <hi>G. E.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Wright,</hi> 1609.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21861:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21861:2"/>
            <head>To the right honorable his very good Lord and patrone, <hi>Henry Fynes</hi> Knight, Lord Clinton and <hi>Say, Earle of Lincolne,</hi> Io: Hoskin <hi>wiſheth</hi> health, honor, and happineſſe in this <hi>life, and in the life to come eternall felicitie.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Ntring of late (right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable) into ſome extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary conſideration, of the common cruelty, and horrible oppreſſion dayly committed, by many couetous cormo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, and cankred Catter-pillets, of this moſt miſerable age wherein we liue, who delight (as the Prophet ſaith) <hi>in nothing but in ioyning houſe to houſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 5 8.</note> 
               <hi>and field to field, till the poore can get no habitation,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be in ſome priſon or other, (where ſome of theſe wicked wretches will not ſtick to ſay, they liue better then they do abroad. (Indeed, as ſome of them vſe
<pb facs="tcp:21861:3"/>them,) and then waying with my ſelfe how vile a monſter, nay, how heinous, and helliſh an <hi>Hydra,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 36.5. &amp; 108.4 Gen. 1.26</note> 
               <hi>Barbarous Cruelty</hi> is, both in the ſight of God, <hi>(whoſe mercy is greater then the heauens)</hi> and in the eyes of good men <hi>(made after his owne Image)</hi> which is many wayes more practiſed and put in execution, now in the light or the Goſpell, amongſt the profeſſors of the ſame, which beare the name of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, then euer it was, either in the time of darkeneſſe and ignorance, or amongſt the Heathen that neuer heard of God. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, beeing fully perſwaded that your Lordſhip is both a profeſſed foe, and an open enemie, to all bloud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>Cains,</hi> and couetous <hi>Ahabs,</hi> that any way ſeeke the ſubuerſion of their poore brothers, or neighbors, ſpirituall, or temporall, either by might, or pollicie. I therefore, being <hi>minimus apoſtolorum,</hi> whoſe arrowes are feathered with foule Misfortune, and whoſe ſunne-ſhine of proſperitie, and warme dayes of well-fare, haue beene Eclipſed with the black clouds of cruelty, and nipping froſts of nine yeares moſt pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tileſſe impriſonment, haue not onely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſed
<pb facs="tcp:21861:3"/>to pen this ſimple tract, of the euill ſeruant toward his poore fellow,<note place="margin">Mat. 18.23.</note> but alſo preſumed to preſent the ſame vnto your honorable view, and Chriſtian con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, ſuppoſing no man more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy then your Lordſhip of a farre fairer peece of worke then it is; not doubting but your honor will vouchſafe, not onely to acce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t thereof, <hi>as the poore widdowes mite,</hi> with as much kindneſſe, as I offer it with good-will, but alſo defend it, vnder the ſhadow of your ſhelter, whereby it ſhall bee ſafe, from the in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ection of infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous tongues. And although I haue not ſtreined vp my ſtrings to any high pitche, whereby to make any great ſound, fine melody, or muſicall harmonie, with <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheus</hi> Harpe to moue dumbe, yea ſenſleſſe creatures (as it were) to liſten therevnto, ſo foming out the frothe of mans wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, in making a great ſhew of learning (for that is not the marke I ſhoote at) but onely the ſaluation of mens ſoules, <hi>for whom Chriſt dyed.</hi>) Therefore accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the capacitie of the common ſort, I haue tuned mine inſtrument with <hi>Hypar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyons</hi> Pipe, to play by the plaineſt mood,
<pb facs="tcp:21861:4"/>at the loweſt Key, and ſweeteſt ſound, thereby to mooue reaſonable men (if it might be) to learne ſome-thing, towards the ſaluation of their poore ſoules, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>wee are not ſent to Preach with wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of words,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.17.27. &amp; 14.19.</note> 
               <hi>for fiue words to edifying is better then ten thouſand not vnderſtood.</hi> Wherein if I haue any wayes paſſed the bound of modeſtie, whereby to offend your Lordſhips patience, or committed any thing diſtaſtfull to your honorable conceit, I moſt humbly craue pardon for the ſame, attending to receiue the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment due to mine imperfections. But if I haue pleaſed the leaſt part of your Lordſhips good liking, I ſhall moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily reſt contented at the dore of your deuotion, and loweſt ſtep of your foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoole. And ſo leauing the crew of all <hi>curſed Caines,</hi> and all couetous <hi>Ahabs,</hi> with all ſuch canker-wormes of crueltie and mercileſſe miſers, in the midſt and maine ſea of their monſtrous mallicious mindes, and your Lordſhip as a moſt worthy pillar, and protector of all poore oppreſſed perſons, to weede out the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and defend the innocent, with the
<pb facs="tcp:21861:4"/>ſworde of Iuſtice, whereby <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Charitie</hi> may bee well planted, the Kings Maieſtie the better preſerued, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth beſt gouerned, and God moſt of all glorified, I moſt humbly take my leaue. <hi>From the Fleete.</hi> 1608.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours poore diſtreſſed, in all Chriſtian dutie euer to be commanded: IO: HOSKIN, Miniſter of Gods word. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. yeares priſoner.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21861:5"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Beſeech you by the mercies of God, in his ſonne <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and by all the Chriſtian kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which I hope to finde at your hands, to perſwade your ſelues, that what ſo euer I haue ſet downe in this ſimple Treatiſe, is rather to deſcribe the nature of curſed Cruelty, then to taxe any man with the infection of that peſtilent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe and helliſh humor, The labour is but ſhort, the Sence plaine, whoſe ſubſtance I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre eyther to the cenſure of your courteous diſcretion, or kindneſſe of your gentle cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and ſo with my vnfeined loue to your good deſert, I rest as cauſe ſhall require.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours euer in the Lord,</hi> IO: HOSKIN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:21861:5"/>
            <head>The Parable of the king <hi>and his euill ſeruant.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Math. 18.23.</bibl>
                  <p>The kingdome of heauen is likened vnto a certaine King, which would take an accoumpt of his ſeruants.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ccording to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation, and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the learned and antient Fathers, there are ſeaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Parables of great conſolation and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, declared and ſet downe by our Lord and Sauiour <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> at ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall times in the holy Goſpell. Amongſt the which, this, touching the forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ten thouſand Talents, is one of the chiefe, wherein the holy ſpirit of GOD, doth not onely breath this, but with-all doth teach vs a moſt neceſſarie dutie of Chriſtian charitie, which the Heathen knew not, and many that beare the name of Chriſtians, ſay they know, but will neither vſe, nor practiſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their poore bretheren, which the
<pb facs="tcp:21861:6"/>Apoſtle calleth <hi>forbearing and forgiuing one another.</hi> Which is ſo neceſſarie a diſpoſition,<note place="margin">Coll. 13.3</note> as that our Sauiour Chriſt the author thereof, doth annexe and ioyne it vnto his prayer, in the holy Goſpell, ſaying, <hi>Except yee forgiue men their treſpaſſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6.15.</note> 
               <hi>your heauenly father will not forgiue you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The occaſion hereof was the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which Saint <hi>Peter</hi> mooued vnto our Sauiour Chriſt, <hi>verſe. 21. How oft ſhall I forgiue my brother? vnto ſeauen times?</hi> wherein he preſumeth two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt that men muſt forgiue.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, that they muſt forgiue more then once. For there is a genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the world that come of the ſéede of curſſed <hi>Caine,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Lamech</hi> was, who will put vp no wrong, nor (as they ſay) do no right, but will bee reuenged like him <hi>ſeuentie times ſeauen times,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 4 24 Rom. 2.4</note> ſcoffing (as it were) <hi>at the long ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of God,</hi> in not puniſhing <hi>Cain,</hi> for killing his brother <hi>Abell.</hi> As though God would ſuffer him to murther his brother, and not be reuenged of ſuch monſtrous cruelty. Yes, <hi>mihi vindicta &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:21861:6"/>ego rependam:</hi> vengeance is mine,<note place="margin">Ro. 12.19</note> and I will repay, ſaith the Lord.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, the Apoſtle preſumeth, that a man muſt forgiue more then once, becauſe the Heathen that knew not God, would forgiue once, but no more, who condemne many that beare the name of Chriſtians, and profeſſe the Goſpell, yea ſuch as ought to be exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of loue, and charitie vnto others, who will not forgiue any one iniurie (be it neuer ſo ſmall) but will be reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged one way or other, <hi>Quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> iure, quaque iniura,</hi> either by law, or by violence, for euery trifle: nay, as <hi>Tully</hi> ſaith, <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulli agrediuntur ad iniuriam faciendum, vt adipiſcantur ea quae concupierunt.</hi> There be ſome that enterpriſe to doe iniurie, that they may obteine thoſe things, which they couet and deſire, cleane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the word of God, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth <hi>all men to do as they would be done vnto.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 7.12</note> But <hi>hij petunt inferas vt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant verum eſſe in morte,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ambro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>quod in vita cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere noluerunt,</hi> Theſe goe to the Deuill, that they may learne, it to bee true at their death, which they would not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue
<pb facs="tcp:21861:7"/>all their life time.</p>
            <p>Againe, there be ſome that thinke, that <hi>Peters</hi> meaning is, by this queſtion, to learne of our Sauiour <hi>Chriſt,</hi> whether a man hauing forgiuen ſeauen iniuries, may afterwards be reuenged, if occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be offered. Others thinke his que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is, as if he ſaid, it is too much: ſhall I forgiue till ſeauen times? but our Lord and maiſter <hi>Chriſt,</hi> (the true pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne of Chriſtian charitie,) anſwering this his queſtion, excéedeth <hi>Peters</hi> expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: ſaying, <hi>not ſeauen times: but ſeuenty times ſeuen times,</hi> which is <hi>490. verſ. 22.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> The doctrine whereof teacheth vs thus much, <hi>viz</hi> that all ſuch as belong vnto <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſhould be as bountifull in mercy, forgiueneſſe, loue and charitie, as <hi>Lamech</hi> profeſſed he would be in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, mallice, wrong and cruelty. For by mercy, loue and charity, <hi>wee are knowne to be the Diſciples of Chriſt, and children of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 13.35.</note> But by reuenge and crueltie, the very impes of hell, and dat lings of the Deuill,<note place="margin">Iam. 2.13</note> 
               <hi>for there ſhall bee condemnation mercileſſe to him that
<pb facs="tcp:21861:7"/>ſheweth no mercy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Doctr.</note> From hence alſo we learne, that it is no wiſe mans courſe, to determine, how farre we ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend our mercy: for ſaith our Sauiour <hi>Chriſt, thy mercy is the meaſure of ioy: <hi>ſicut et ego tibi,</hi>
               </hi> euen as I had pittie on thée <hi>verſ. 33.</hi> ſo ſhould we.</p>
            <p>But ſuch as would haue a certaine number ſet downe, how oft they ſhould forgiue their brother, and a proportion for practiſing of their mercy: deſire that GOD ſhould forgiue them a certaine number of times, &amp; afterwards powre downe his anger, and heauie wrath vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them.</p>
            <p>The Key of the opening and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of this Parable,<note place="margin">Expoſitio at diuiſio.</note> is <hi>verſ. 35.</hi> where the King is the heauenly father, we the ſeruants; The debt ſinne, and the fallow, ſeruants our poore neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and Chriſtian bretheren.</p>
            <p>In this Parable (as the antient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers doe note) there are two parts, a white part, and a black, <hi>viz.</hi> a good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to be followed, and a bad to bee eſchewed and auoyded; as wee are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted by the Prophets. <hi>Eſchew euill,
<pb facs="tcp:21861:8"/>and doe good,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 34.13 Iſa. 1.16.17</note> 
               <hi>ſeeke iudgement, releeue the oppreſſed, &amp;c.</hi> Or if we diuide it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the King himſelfe, there we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold,<note place="margin">Ro. 11, 22</note> both <hi>the bountifulneſſe and ſeueri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Firſt the great mercy and boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the King, in forgiuing his ſeruant a debt of ten thouſand Talents.</item>
               <item>2. Secondly his ſeueritie, in turning his debt vpon his bead, who hauing bin forgiuen a great debt, would not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue his fellow ſeruant a ſmall debt.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The white part.</note>In the former part there are two things to be conſidered.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Firſt, the perſons; which are two.</item>
               <item>2. Secondly, the procéedings, which are of iuſtice. The procéedings accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to iuſtice, are declared in the <hi>25. ver.</hi> where it is ſaid, <hi>becauſe he had nothing to pay, his Lord commanded him to bee ſould, &amp;c.</hi> The procéedings according to mercy, <hi>verſ. 27. his Lord had compaſſion and looſed him, and forgaue him, &amp;c.</hi> Either of which, I could wiſh were exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted now adayes amongſt vs, that beare the name of Chriſtians, &amp; profeſſe the Goſpell, for then there ſhould not
<pb facs="tcp:21861:8"/>ſo many poore men pine and periſh in priſon, to the vtter vndooing of their wiues and children for euer.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Whereby we may ſée euidently, that the procéedings of mercy, which conſiſt in our imitation, and which we ought to practiſe, are vtterly neglected and aboliſhed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In the black part, firſt we are to obſerue,<note place="margin">The blacke part.</note> how the euill ſeruant (being forgiuen) behaued himſelfe towards his fellow ſeruant, which is to be ſéene, <hi>verſ. 28. &amp; 30. Taking him by the throate and caſting him in priſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly how he was ſerued, for his barbarous &amp; moſt cruell dealings, which alſo conſiſteth of two parts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Firſt in reſpect of his fellow ſeruants.</item>
               <item>2. Secondly in reſpect of his maiſter.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Generally we are to learne &amp; obſerue thus much, that this is a plaine mirror of Gods great mercie and goodneſſe, who requireth nothing of vs, but what he firſt performeth towards vs: as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>in hoc comendar charitatem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5.8.</note> in this God ſeeteth out his loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs, that when we were ſinners
<pb facs="tcp:21861:9"/>Chriſt dyed for vs. And therefore it is but equall dealing, that we ſhould (after his example) ſhew mercy vnto our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: and we muſt not onely doe to an other, as we would haue others doe to vs (which the law of nature teacheth vs to bee equall) but as wee would haue God do vnto vs. For wee muſt forgiue our brethren, not onely as wee would haue them forgiue vs, but as we looke, and hope to be forgiuen at the hands of Almighty God.</p>
            <p>Now for the perſons: and firſt for the King, which is Almighty God, who ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth out himſelfe in the Scriptures, by ſundry reſemblances, as to <hi>an husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, a Sheepheard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 13 Ioh. 10.</note> 
               <hi>a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſher, a Merchan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and here a King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in this there is a very déepe reach, for our nature is ſo bewitched, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times, we thinke that the practiſe of godly and Chriſtian vertues, will vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſgrace vs, as it is gathered by the ancient Fathers vpon the Canticles, where it is ſaid,<note place="margin">Can. 5.3.</note> 
               <hi>I haue put off my coate, how ſhall I put it on? I haue waſhed my feete, how ſhall I defile them?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21861:9"/>
            <p>If we forgiue any little wrong that is offered vs (eſpecially by our inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours,) nay if they doe not patiently en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, and quietly put vp, any cruell, and intollerable iniuries, and open wrongs, that we do offer vnto them,<note place="margin">Iniury of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered three wayes.</note> we thinke our ſelues both much abuſed, &amp; foulie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed, whether it be in their body, goods or name, yea many, but vpon a ſuppoſed offence, will not onely offer iniurie, but alſo ſéeke reuenge for the ſame, yea euen vnto the death, which is a moſt deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble furie, far paſſing the nature of wilde beaſts, which ſpare the bloud of their ſexe. Therfore ſaith <hi>Socrates,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Socrat.</note> 
               <hi>Reuenge is not in any ſort to be vſed, nor is it iuſt to offend any, although hee had offered vs wrong: for the Lord is the auenger of all ſuch things, <hi>&amp; oppreſſo in refugium,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.6 Pſal. 9.9.</note> 
               <hi>and defence for the oppreſſed:</hi> but we neuer remember it.</p>
            <p>Our heauenly father (when he will teach vs this moſt excellent vertue of mercy) bringeth in himſelfe as a King, to teach vs that it is a princely thing to forgiue, for ſo ſaith <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe,<note place="margin">Mat. 9.13. pro. 21.3.</note> 
               <hi>I wil haue mercy &amp; not ſacrifice.</hi> that is, what
<pb facs="tcp:21861:10"/>care I for your ſacrifices, as long as your liues, and conuerſations are wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and full of pride, oppreſſion, coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, vſury, bribery, extortion, adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, murder, drunkenneſſe, Idolatrie, mallice, e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, vndooing and deuonring of each other, &amp;c.<note place="margin">Mat. 5.24 &amp; 6.12.</note> And therefore exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs vnto <hi>reconciliation, before wee come to offer any gift,</hi> elſe it is but in vaine to pray, <hi>forgiue vs our treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore forgiue thy neighbor the hurt that hee hath done vnto thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e. 28.2.3.4.</note> 
               <hi>ſo ſhall thy ſinnes bee forgiuen thee alſo, when thou praieſt. For ſhould a man beare hatred againſt man? and deſire forgiueneſſe of the Lord? hee will ſhew no mercy to a man, which is like himſelfe, and will hee aske forgiueneſſe of his owne ſinnes? If hee that is but fleſh nouriſh hatred, and aske pardon of God, who will intreate for his ſinnes?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 103.8</note> Therefore <hi>remember the end, and let enmitie paſſe;</hi> for <hi>miſericors &amp; clemens est dominus.</hi> The Lord is full of compaſſion and mercy, whoſe exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple wee ought to follow. And, <hi>Pius quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidie miſeretur &amp; dat mutuum,</hi> a good
<pb facs="tcp:21861:10"/>man is euer mercifull and lendeth, ſaith the Prophet, preferring mercy before iudgment i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his ſong,<note place="margin">Pſa. 37.26. &amp; 101.1. Iam. 2.13. Luc. 6.13.</note> 
               <hi>and mercy reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth againſt iudgement. Therefore bee mercifull, as your heauenly Father is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull.</hi> For God had rather want the ſacrifice due vnto him,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> then mercy and reconciliation ſhould bee wanting, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt thée and thy brother</p>
            <p>To pardon and forgiue,<note place="margin">Pittacus.</note> is the part of a man, to reuenge is the part of a beaſt. Then how many beaſts be there now adayes amongſt vs, who voyde of all mercy, pitty, or any ſparke of compaſſion, ſéeke not onely reuenge, but the vtter ſpoile, ſubuerſion, and diſtruction <hi>of their poore neighbours,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos 4.1</note> 
               <hi>and needy brethren, who would faine dwell in quiet by them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 3.29. &amp; 24.15. &amp; 22.23.</note> Therefore <hi>ſpoyle not his reſting place: for the Lord will ſpoile the ſoule of them that ſpoile them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>Athens</hi> there was a Temple dedicated vnto <hi>Mercy,</hi> into the which none might enter that were not helpe-full and beneficiall vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which cauſed the people, but
<pb facs="tcp:21861:11"/>eſpecially the Magiſtrates, and men of authority and calling, to ſtudie and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerciſe works of pitty and piety, through a deſire, which they had to enter there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. Now therefore if they which had not any knowledge of God nor his word, in reſpect of that which we haue now, in the light of the Goſpell, did ſo much reſpect the workes of mercie, and compaſſion, pitty and piety, for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire they had to enter into an earthly temple: what ought wee to doe for the entrance into the celeſtiall and euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing temple of the Lord, and the endleſſe habitation in the ſame,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.9</note> where <hi>there are ſuch ioyes as no mortall eyes haue ſeene, eares haue heard, tongue can expreſſe, or heart conceine?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> aſketh,<note place="margin">Pſal. 15.1.2.3.</note> 
               <hi>quis habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabit in tabernaculo domini? <hi>Who ſhall dwell in the holy temple of the Lord?</hi>
               </hi> and anſwereth: <hi>Qui operatur iuſtitiam; neque fecit malum proximo ſuo. <hi>He that worketh righteouſneſſe, and hath not done euill to his neighbour.</hi>
               </hi> None elſe? no. Then what ſhall become of all tyrants, oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, bloudy builders, murderers, back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biters,
<pb facs="tcp:21861:11"/>ſtanderers, biting vſurers, bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, extortioners, couetous perſons, that take rewards againſt the innocent? &amp; ſuch like, as falſe ſwearers, &amp; knights of the poſt? and thoſe that vſe falſe weights and meaſures? ſurely theſe, and all ſuch (without ſpéedy and vnfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned repentance) muſt néedes fall and be caſt downe, with that mercileſſe <hi>churle into hell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luc. 16.</note> who would ſhew no mercy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to poore <hi>Lazarus,</hi> as the Prophet affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, ſaying: <hi>Conuertentur impy in infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, et omnes gentes, qui obliuiſcuntur dei. <hi>The wicked ſhall be turned into hell,</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 9.17.</note> 
               <hi>and all the people that forget God,</hi> who is the fountain of all mercy, pitty &amp; compaſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>Therfore let all bloudy <hi>Cains,</hi> théeniſh. <hi>Achans,</hi> bribing <hi>Gehezies,</hi> couetous <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habs</hi> and <hi>Iezebels, all Labans</hi> and <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balls,</hi> with all the rable of rent-rackers, take héed and remember, that <hi>Dominus ſibi virum pium ſegregauit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 4.3. &amp; 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>the Lord hath choſen to himſelfe the man that is godly. <hi>Sed qui loquuntur mendacium, &amp; virum ſanguinum abhominabitur,</hi> but abhorreth both the lyer, and blood-thirſty man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Man is called <hi>homo,</hi> from whence this
<pb facs="tcp:21861:12"/>word <hi>humanitas</hi> is deriued, which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth curteſie, or gentleneſſe, for which cauſe <hi>Plato</hi> calleth him a ciuill creature,<note place="margin">Plato.</note> by nature ſociable and mercifull, and therefore ſaith, that Mercy ought no more to be taken away from the nature of man, then the altar out of the temple. <hi>The ſinner deſpiſeth his neighbour</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 14.21</note> 
               <hi>but hee that is mercifull to the poore is bleſſed, and he that hath pitty on the poore lendeth vnto the Lord, who will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ecompence him that which he hath giuen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">&amp; 19.17.</note> I might alleadge many reaſons &amp; diuerſe arguments,<note place="margin">1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> to mooue vs vnto lous and charity, pitty and mercy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our poore brethren &amp; néedy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours: as firſt the creation of man <hi>after the Image of God,</hi> wherevnto we owe all honor,<note place="margin">Pſa 2 Gen. 1.26.</note> loue, and obedience. Secondly the re-eſtabliſhment into the ſame I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage by his pure grace &amp; mercy. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie the contemplation &amp; building of this glorious frame of man, with the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent compoſition thereof, in whom the brightnes and grace of God ſhineth, but eſpecially in thoſe whom the world de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth. Further, if we did but conſider,
<pb facs="tcp:21861:12"/>that we are of one mould, haue one ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, and one God, who promiſeth to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept as done to himſelfe,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.</note> 
               <hi>what good ſo euer we doe to one of his little ones,</hi> of whom, ſome for want of ſuccour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, are ready to ſtarue in the ſtréetes, others pine and periſh in priſon,<note place="margin">Ier 7.5.6. &amp; 22.3. Looke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</note> and all for want of the due execution of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and iuſtice, as well towards the riche as the poore, the creditor as the debtor, wherby the widdow and father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, the innocent and friendleſſe, are ſtill oppreſſed, ſome time by delayes, ſome time by demurres, and ſome time by <hi>ad idem in proximum,</hi> (which things are good in themſelues, but being abuſed are very bad) and many times bribes <hi>blind the eyes of the wiſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exo. 23.15. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u, 16</note> 
               <hi>&amp; peruert true iudgement, but woe vnto the bribers and extortioners.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 22.15. Prou. 18.5. Mich. 3. Pro. 17.22.</note> Did not their fathers liue well and proſper, when they executed iuſtice without reſpect of perſons? But they haue peruerted all equity, &amp; abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red iudgment, and iudged for rewardes: And thus <hi>the peoples skinnes are puld and pluckt from their backes:</hi> thus they are bought and ſolde for old ſhooes:<note place="margin">Amos. 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <pb facs="tcp:21861:13"/>and thus they are <hi>eaten vp and deuoured like bread,</hi> whereas we ought not onely to do good,<note place="margin">Pſa 14.8 Galla.</note> &amp; ſhew mercy vnto all men, but euen to them that do vs wrong and hate vs: according to our Sauiour <hi>Chriſts</hi> commandement: <hi>Loue your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, bleſſe them that curſſe you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5.44</note> 
               <hi>do good to them that hate you, and pray for them that perſecute you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was a great perſon, yet thought it no diſgrace to forgiue his brethren.<note place="margin">Gen 25.15. 1. Sam. 24 2. Sam. 16 Acts 7.60 Lu 23.34 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. pro. 20.28</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> a King, <hi>did ſhew mercy vnto his enimie <hi>Saul,</hi>
               </hi> and forgaue <hi>Shemei <hi>his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence in curſing him,</hi> Steuen <hi>them that ſtoned him, and our</hi> Sauiour Chriſt <hi>thoſe that put him to death.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus we ſée it is not onely a princely, but alſo a moſt diuine thing to pardon and forgiue our brethren: for the King that here ſetteth forth him as an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is God himſelfe. Therefore if wee will be honorable, or ſo accompted, we muſt learne our termes of honor from our Lord and maiſter <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> &amp; not from the race of curſed <hi>Cain,</hi> or reueng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Lamech.</hi> And the more honorable that a man is, ſo much the more it is his
<pb facs="tcp:21861:13"/>honor, to be moſt ready to forgiue, and put vp wrong, without ſéeking reuenge: but as the Prophet ſaith;<note place="margin">Pſ. 49. vlt. Eccl. 3 18</note> 
               <hi>Homo in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nore non intelliget, ſed comparatur immentis quae intereunt, <hi>Man being in honor, hath no vnderſtanding, but may be compared vnto the beaſts that periſh;</hi>
               </hi> eſpecially when they vndooe their poore brethren, by oppreſſion, ſuites in lawe, frawde, or impriſonment, for euery light occaſion. Nay, without any iuſt cauſe,<note place="margin">A prouerb.</note> but it is an old ſaying, <hi>Where the hedge is loweſt, the beaſt ſooneſt goeth ouer, and the weakeſt are ſooneſt put to the worſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard in Can.</note> Therefore I may ſay with that old Father; If beaſts could ſpeake, they would call ſuch wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men beaſts, and farre worſe.<note place="margin">August.</note> For as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith: Brute beaſts do rauen but when they are hungry, and being full do ſpare the prey. But theſe beaſts, the more they haue, the more they rauen and ſpoile, whereby it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, they neither feare God in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, King on earth, nor deuill in hell. <hi>Creſcit amor nummi quantum ipſa pecunia creſcit: <hi>The loue of money encreaſeth as the money it ſelfe encreaſeth:</hi>
               </hi> the more
<pb facs="tcp:21861:14"/>they haue the more they deſire, like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re, the more wodde the more heate: therefore the couetous mans heart is compared vnto a bottomleſſe purſſe, which is neuer full: or like the <hi>Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leche</hi> that <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeaketh of,<note place="margin">Pro. 30.15 16</note> 
               <hi>the graue and the barren wombe,</hi> which will neuer be ſatiſfied.</p>
            <p>Thus the poore <hi>are threſhed to death with Flailes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos. 1.3</note> as the Prophet ſaith: this is the malicious ſinne which <hi>Dauid</hi> prayeth againſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 59.5</note> ſaying, <hi>Ne miſerearis omnibus qui peruerſe et inique agunt: <hi>bee not mercifull to them that offend of mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice:</hi>
               </hi> for as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith, <hi>fire ſhall conſume their houſes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 15.34</note>
            </p>
            <p>I would that ſuch cruell men, and ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of reuenge, would remember the words and déeds of <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon,</hi> who when it was told him that one <hi>Nicanor</hi> (a néedy fellow) did ſpeake euill of him, becauſe hee neuer did him good, the kings ſeruants gaue him coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell to puniſh him. Nay quoth the King, not ſo. I ſuppoſe be is a good man, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it were better to ſearch firſt if the fault be not in vs. The King vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:21861:14"/>that <hi>Nicanor</hi> was a poore man, ſent him a rich preſent, wherevpon after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards this fellow ſpake as much good of the king openly for his bountie, as euer he did euill of him for his couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Whereby we ſée it is in the power of great men themſelues, to cauſe either euill or good to be ſpoken of them.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe <hi>Antigonus</hi> King of <hi>Macedon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Antigon.</note> hearing himſelfe euill ſpoken of by ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers hard by his tent, came forth vnto them, and ſaid nothing but thus. Good Lord could you not haue gene farther off, to haue ſpoken euill of me? Thus far off were theſe two Kings from reueng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their owne priuate quarrels, which might be a good example vnto all men of what eſtate or degrée ſo euer they bee, how they ſéeke reuenge againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore.</p>
            <p>But now <hi>tempora mutaneur et nos muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur in illis,</hi> the caſe is cleane altred, for euery man (for the moſt part) will moſt cruelly reuenge the iniuries done to himſelfe, &amp; pardon thoſe which are done againſt other, yea many times, although they be directly againſt the law &amp; honor of God.<note place="margin">Xenoph.</note> And therfore as <hi>Zenophon</hi> ſaith
<pb facs="tcp:21861:15"/>in his <hi>Cyropaedia,</hi> let euery one ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue himſelfe to wards his enemy, as at ſome time or other hee may thinke to haue him his friend.</p>
            <p>Secondly now touching the ſeruants, wherein we haue <hi>4.</hi> things to obſerue.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that ſinne hath the nature of a debt, for ſo our Sauiour <hi>Chriſt</hi> teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs to pray: <hi>forgiue vs our debts,</hi> and ſo ſinners are called debtors, as <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> was,<note place="margin">Luc. 16.5 Luc. 7.47</note> 
               <hi>who had her ſinnes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen her,</hi> which afore were accompted debts. For the caſe of the law, it is as an obligation, wherein if the condition be not kept, we do incurre the penaltie.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we are to note a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt ſinnes and debts. For ſinnes, which are againſt God, are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared vnto talents: ſinnes againſt our brethren, are but as pence.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the debt is not of one, but of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thouſand talents: <hi>hec no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſumma, est maſſa,</hi> this is not a ſumme, but a mas of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. And as before, we ſaw the enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of ſinne, ſo here we may beholde the multitude of our ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, it is ſaid, <hi>adductus est,</hi> hée
<pb facs="tcp:21861:15"/>was brought: which bringing, ſheweth that he neuer tooke care, or any thought,<note place="margin">A ſecure ſinner.</note> how to pay his debt. He eate his meate and tooke his reſt, hee liued merily, and quietly, in pompe and pleaſure, which is the caſe of many now adayes, in reſpect of ſinne, wherein moſt ſecurely they are lulled and rocked faſt a ſléepe, yet their caſe is moſt dangerous, and moſt lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and nothing elſe, but that which our Sauiour <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſpeaketh of in the Goſpel <hi>Fortis ſic omnia poſſidet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luc. 11.21</note> 
               <hi>the ſtrong man poſſeſſeth all things ſo in peace;</hi> as for example,<note place="margin">Simile.</note> a Captaine hauing quiet poſſeſſion of a caſtle or ſtrong hold, what néedeth he to make any broiles, or brabbles? euen ſo it is with our aduer ſary the Deuill, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>c omnia poſſidet,</hi> doth ſo quietly poſſeſſe the hearts and mindes, (which are as the Caſtles and holdes of many couetous wretched worldlings) and hath ſo rocked them a ſléepe in the <hi>Cradle of Securitie,</hi> that they neuer make any accompt of many ſinnes which they dayly commit, both againſt God &amp; man: eſpecially of pettie ſinnes, as ieſting, ſcurrulous talke, wantonneſſe, idleneſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:21861:16"/>and riotous expences, &amp;c. for the which they ſcorne to be controuled or admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed of by any man, which is a token of reprobation: for let all ſuch know, that as many ſmall drops of raine do make a great floud, able to drowne both horſe and man, ſo many ſmall ſinnes do make a great and dangerous deluge, able to drowne both body and ſoule.</p>
            <p>Therfore ſaith the Pſalmiſt,<note place="margin">Pſa. 38.18</note> 
               <hi>Cogitabo, et anxius ero pro peccato <hi>I will confeſſe my wickedneſſe, and bee ſory for my ſinne.</hi>
               </hi> And,<note place="margin">&amp; 32.6.</note> 
               <hi>confeſſionem faciam de peccatis meis domino, et tu remiſiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, iniquitatem peccati mei: <hi>I will confeſſe my ſinnes vnto the Lord, and thou forgaueſt the wickedneſſe of my ſinne.</hi>
               </hi> According to that ſaving of <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> 
               <hi>Audiui regem dicentem peccani Domino, et Prophetam reſpondentem tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulit dominus peccatum tuum a te. <hi>I heard the King ſay I haue ſinned againſt the Lord, and the Prophet make anſwer: the Lord hath taken thy ſinnes from thee.</hi>
               </hi> Therefore the wiſe mans aduiſe is,<note place="margin">Pro. 6.8</note> 
               <hi>if thou bee ſurety for another,</hi> humble thy ſelfe, and vſe all meanes to diſcharge the debt: till then giue thine eyes no
<pb facs="tcp:21861:16"/>ſléepe. But this fellow taketh no ſuch order, but was ſecure and careleſſe, and ſo was fit to be brought.</p>
            <p>Such is our ſecuritie in reſpect of ſinne, we take no thought for it, we nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtriue by prayer againſt it, before we commit it, nor yet are we humbled after it, but many are ſuch as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeaketh of,<note place="margin">Pro. 2.11</note> 
               <hi>Qui letantur cum male fece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint, et exultent in rebus peſſimis, <hi>they are glad when they haue done euill, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in things moſt wicked:</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Simile.</note> vntill God by ſome croſſe or affliction, by ſome meanes or other bring vs vnder an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt. Such may fitly be compared vnto théeues in a Iayle, who neuer remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the aſſiſes, vntill the iudge come riding in at townes end. Nay rather like condemned felons, who fall meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye to gaming, ſport, and paſtime with the halters about their necks, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with their breath muſt bee ſtopped. Euen ſo, many ſecure ſinners ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thinke on their ende, vntill vg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glye Death arreſt and ſeize vppon them: and what is this? but euen, <hi>the Oxe to the ſlaughter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 7.22</note> 
               <hi>and the foole
<pb facs="tcp:21861:17"/>to the ſtocks,</hi> neuer thinking of death or puniſhment, which is a moſt wofull caſe, the Lord amend it.</p>
            <p>There is alſo an other kind of ſinners,<note place="margin">A deſperat ſinner.</note> who being but weake in minde and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, &amp; not well acquainted with the ſwéet promiſes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel, being prick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d in conſcience with the burden of their ſins &amp; then remembring the curſſe of the law due for the ſame, which no man is, (or euer was) able to beare, but only our Sauiour <hi>Chriſt:</hi> alas, what a miſerable caſe are theſe in? let them remember that <hi>at what time ſoeuer a ſinner doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent him of his ſinnes from the bottome of his heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eze. 18.21</note> 
               <hi>the Lord will blot them out of his remembrance, &amp; that the ſeruants Lord had compaſſion, and forgaue him the debt, as ſoone as hee humbly beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>an.</note> 
               <hi>27. <hi>verſe.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for the two procéedings: and firſt of Iuſtice. Iuſtice as ſaith <hi>Lactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> in reſpect of God, is called godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but in reſpect of our ſelues, &amp; our dealings with men,<note place="margin">Cicero.</note> it is taken for an equall diſtribution of right, &amp; of lawes, and as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith, it is a perpetuall
<pb facs="tcp:21861:17"/>and a conſtant deſire, and good will to giue euery one his right, and his owne, eſpecially as the party is greater, chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the King muſt haue his right: but in reſpect of God, and the duties which we are to performe vnto him, if he ſhould take an accompt of vs,<note place="margin">Iob. 9.3.</note> 
               <hi>wee are not able to anſwer him one of a thouſand,</hi> and as the Pſalmiſt ſaith, <hi>Si niquitates obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris domine quis conſiſtet?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 103.3</note> 
               <hi>If thou ſhouldeſt bee extreame to marke what is done amiſſe, O Lord who may abide it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then if not able to pay (which was the caſe of this ſeruant) all his goods muſt be praiſed, and ſale muſt bee made according to the law; but not as many vnder Sheriffes and common Bayliffes doe often times in the countrie with poore mens goods,<note place="margin">Nota, quam iniuriam, in ſons ego ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, bis ſuſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li. imo om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia omnin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> perdidi.</note> playing ſwéepe-ſtake for their owne aduantage and gaine, whereby the poore debtor, his wife and children are vtterly vndone, becauſe his goods are praiſed and ſold, not at a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the rate which they are worth, and neuer can haue them againe of which hard dealings, I haue béene <hi>Occulatus teſtis,</hi> but as <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſayd to the poore
<pb facs="tcp:21861:18"/>widdow:<note place="margin">1. Reg. 4.7.</note> 
               <hi>ſell thy oyle and pay thy debts, and liue vpon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt.</hi> So doth the King command him, his wife and children, and all that he had, ſo be ſolde, and pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be made, <hi>verſ. 25.</hi> which were a happy courſe for many poore men, which commonly pine and periſh in priſon, by the cruelty of the creditors, there ſpend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that little which they haue, and at length there leauing their liues, as Snakes doe their Hackles in old hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, whereby the leanneſſe of impoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed perſons, make fatte priſons, and Iaylers Gentlemen: where ten ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings a wéeke for a bare Chamber and a bed-ſtead, is nothing; where ſeuentie pound a yeare for a drunken Taphouſe is but a little, elſe how ſhould the rent of a Iayle bee at a thouſand pound a yeare.</p>
            <p>But <hi>ad rem,</hi> I know this lawe of ſale which the King commanded to bee made, nor the doctrine thereof, neither taſteth well in the mouthes, nor is it pleaſant in the ſtomackes of thoſe, whome wee in plaine Engliſh call <hi>Bankrupts:</hi> who vpon credit, will take
<pb facs="tcp:21861:18"/>vp as much money and goods, as they can gette into their hands, and then breake (as they call it) with their Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors, contrary to their promiſe, bonds, faith, and all honeſtie, taking vp their lodging in Ludgate, or ſome Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie, and there liuing in eaſe and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, letting out their money to Vſury with a bad conſcience, paying their Creditors with two ſhillings in the pound, or ſome ſuch matter, thinking this no theft, nor any deceit at all, cleane contrary to Saint <hi>Paules</hi> rule,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.8</note> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning debters: <hi>Owe nothing to any man, but this,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 20 17.15</note> 
               <hi>that yee loue one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other,</hi> and the laſt commandement, <hi>thou ſhalt not couet thy neighbours goods, or thou ſhalt not ſteale;</hi> thooſe yée which.</p>
            <p>But when the King commeth to take accompt of his ſeruants, <hi>verſ. 23.</hi> they ſhall finde, that all ſuch ſubtill ſhifts, and deceitfull deuiſes ſhall prooue but <hi>Figge leaues,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.7</note> not able to couer their cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed couetouſneſſe; nor yet to defend them from the wrath of him, who is <hi>ſcrutator cordis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 17.10 1. Tim. 4.2</note> 
               <hi>the ſearcher out of their hollow hearts, and ſeard conſciences.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21861:19"/>
            <p>Now if we ſhould apply this to a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituall conſideration, it would fitte vs very well: for as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>wee are all ſold vnder ſinne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7.14 1. Ioh. 5, 19</note> and <hi>totus mundus in maligno poſitus est, <hi>all the world is ſet vpon wickedneſſe:</hi>
               </hi> and as the Prophet ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 14.2. &amp; 53.2.</note> 
               <hi>Corruperunt vias ſuas, abominabile focerunt ſtudium, non est qui facit bonum, <hi>they are all corrupt and become abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable in their doings, there is none that dooth good, no not one.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here I leaue theſe, and goe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to the procéedings of mercy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mercy</hi> being the moſt excellent ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and the ioy of faith, the author whereof is God himſelfe, <hi>whoſe mercy is euerlaſting,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luc. 1.50</note> will heare <hi>the crye of the afflicted,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exe. 22.27 &amp; 4.31.</note> and <hi>wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> neuer forſake them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is mercifull,</hi> yea as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>Prope adeſt Dominus omnibus inuocanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus eum in veritate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 145.18</note> 
               <hi>The Lord is nigh vnto all that call vpon him faithfully:</hi> he heard <hi>Iacob</hi> in all his troubles,<note place="margin">Gen. 35. Exod. 14 1. Sam. 1</note> &amp; <hi>Moſes</hi> when he ſighed and groned, <hi>Anna</hi> that barren woman was not forgotten, nor <hi>Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iel</hi> in the Lions den,<note place="margin">Dan. 3. &amp; 1, 3.</note> nor <hi>Suſanna</hi> amongſt the wicked Iudges, nor the thrée children
<pb facs="tcp:21861:19"/>in the fierie Furnace,<note place="margin">Acts. 11.</note> nor <hi>Peter</hi> in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: and ſo likewiſe, as wee may ſée <hi>verſe. 26.</hi> by this ſeruant, when hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought his maiſter, hee heard him, and had compaſſion vpon him.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> Wherein wee haue to learne, that prayer and humble ſupplication vnto God, is the onely meanes to preſerue vs from condemnation for ſinne: for by that meanes he was forgiuen his debt. <hi>Quiarogaſti, <hi>becauſe thou prayedſt mee, verſ. 32.</hi>
               </hi> For ſo ſaith the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 32.6</note> if a man will be deliuered from his ſinnes, <hi>Pro hoc orabit omnis, <hi>for this ſhall euery one pray.</hi>
               </hi> Aud Saint <hi>Peters</hi> aduice is, <hi>Pray God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts. 8.22</note> 
               <hi>that if it bee poſſible the thoughts of thy heart may bee forgiuen thee:</hi> as that godly Father alſo teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, ſaying: <hi>A te petatur, in te queratur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. lib. confeſ. <hi>13.</hi> cap. vlt.</note> 
               <hi>ad te pulſetur, ſic accipietur, ſic inuonietur, ſic aporietur. <hi>Of thee we muſt aske, at thee we muſt ſeeke, &amp; at thee we muſt knock, ſo we receiue, ſo we finde, and ſo to vs it is opened:</hi>
               </hi> which doctrine is cleane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the vile blaſphemous Papiſts, which pray either vnto ſtocks or ſtones,
<pb facs="tcp:21861:20"/>Images, Saints, Angels, or the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo, here we may ſée, that by a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſure interceſſion, we muſt remooue from the Court of Gods iuſtice, vnto the Court of Gods mercy. And vpon this ſecond procéeding, behold the boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifulneſſe of the King, who for a few words ſpeaking, forgiueth him the debt, when he had nothing to pay, as we read in the Goſpell, he dooth not onely grant him that which hee deſired,<note place="margin">Luc. 24.7</note> which was but forbearance, but alſo much more aboundantly, according to the ſaying of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Eph. 3.20</note> 
               <hi>he is able to doe aboundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie aboue all that wee can aske or deſire.</hi> For whereas he deſired but onely to be forborne, by his humility and prayer he doth obtaine both dylation and remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, be doth not onely forget, but alſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue, and remit the debt: loe here the necoſſitie and effect of himble prayer. And that which is a third thing to bee remembred, turn at that time when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſate vpon his iudgement ſeate, to take a reckoning and ſtrict accompt: as the Prophet ſaith; <hi>He doth in wrath
<pb facs="tcp:21861:20"/>remember mercy,</hi> which is a leſſon,<note place="margin">Hab. 3.2</note> both for Iudges, that ſitte to heare the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of poore diſtreſſed men, and alſo of great conſolation and comfort to all thoſe that are oppreſſed and heauy la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with the burthen of their ſinnes,<note place="margin">Mat. 11.2</note> that the nature of the Deitie is thus ſlowe to wrath, and ready to forgiue, which is or might bee an example vnto all men, but eſpecially vnto great men, and Magiſtrates, that they ſhould immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate this King in mercy, which is Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty GOD, whoſe mercy indéed, ſhould be the example of ours, and our mercy the meaſure of his. For man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a creature made of God, after his owne image, iuſt, holy good,<note place="margin">Gen. 1.2</note> and right by nature, framed of the earth, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired with ſpirit and life, hath his bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and his well being, onely to ſet forth the glory of his Creator, and to ſpeake and do thoſe things which are agréeable vnto him, which is, <hi>to bee mercifull,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exo. 22.27 Luc. 6.36</note> as <hi>hee is mercifull.</hi> Thus we ſée the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and bountie of the King.</p>
            <p>Now ſecondly we are to take a blew how he dealt with his fellow ſeruant.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21861:21"/>
            <p>A body would thinke, that after his impreſſion of feare, that was condenmed to bee ſold, and contrariwiſe, the great affection of loue and compaſſion in the King in forgiuing the debt, vpon his humble intreatie, he would neuer haue forgotten the goodneſſe of his maiſter. But we may ſée it to be true, which the Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">Iam. 4.5 What en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie is.</note> 
               <hi>There is an euill ſpirit which luſteth after enuie,</hi> which is a griefe ariſing at another mans preſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, with which vice this euill ſeruant was fowly enfected, as there bee many now adayes ſick of that diſeaſe, who grudge and grieue, mumble and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure, if they ſée any man thriue, come to any preferment, or haue any good ſucceſſe in his affaires, more then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, or bee accompted honeſter then they: wee our ſelues and euery one, for his owne part,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.2</note> is <hi>ſick of ſelfe-loue,</hi> for we can be content to be well vſed, well ſpoken of, and praiſed: yea, to haue our faults couered, and our offences and debts forgiuen vs, without any ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſitie or quaintneſſe, both at Gods hand and mans, which is a bleſſed thing,
<pb facs="tcp:21861:21"/>as the Prophet ſaith:<note place="margin">Pſal. 32.1</note> but wee cannot finde in our hearts to mete the ſame meaſure againe vnto others, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding our Sauiour <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his holy Goſpell teacheth vs, that <hi>with what meaſure we mete,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 7.2</note> 
               <hi>it ſhall be meaſured to vs againe;</hi> There is in this part thrée carnall ſinnes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt he was his fellow ſeruant, of the ſame eſtate, no ſtranger vnto him, but one that he knew well enough, yea a brother, which hath matter to ſtirre vp compaſſion, eſpecially in any man that hath any ſparke of Chriſtianitie in him.</p>
            <p>God cannot offend man, yet he forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth man: but man may offend man, and yet will not forgiue man, hee might after offend his fellow ſeruant, and therefore ought to forgiue him before he did it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly the debt was no great matter, but an hundred pence, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he might the more eaſily haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen it, for as much as GOD for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaue him a great mas of mony.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, this debt he will not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue,
<pb facs="tcp:21861:22"/>although it be but ſmall, but requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it after a moſt inhumaine and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>age manner, <hi>taking him by the throte, and ſaying, pay mee that thou oweſt, verſ. 28.</hi> To the which wee adde thrée parts more.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt going forth but euen from the preſence of his Maiſter as ſoone as hée had béene forgiuen, hée beginneth to bee vnmercifull, that hauing receiued mercy at Gods hands, he is ſo cruell to his fellow ſeruant, that addeth a great heynouſneſſe vnto his crime.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, in that his fellow vſeth the ſame meanes to him, which he vſed vnto God, <hi>viz. <hi>I pray thee haue patience:</hi> quiarogaſti, <hi>becauſe thou prayedſt mee;</hi>
               </hi> was the reaſon why the Lord forgaue him, yet he will not forgiue his fellow, who vſed the ſame words vnto him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, <hi>non moueri ſaltem conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ontia, <hi>not to be mooued one whit in conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience,</hi>
               </hi> is a hainous fault, but eſpecially not to bee mooued with the example of a King, that hath dealt ſo gratiouſly with him, that is a great wickedneſſe, hee is not onely cruell, but alſo wicked
<pb facs="tcp:21861:22"/>and vnkinde, euen in that wherein hee had found kindneſſe, which alſo addeth very much to his fault: for our Sauiour <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>Cui multum remittitur, <hi>to whom much is forgiuen, ſhe loued much.</hi>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Luc. 7.49</note> Hée had a great debt forgiuen him, and therefore ought, to haue ſhewed his loue in like ſort vnto his fellow ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, in forgiuing him his debt, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our Sauiour <hi>Chriſts</hi> commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>goe thou and doe likewiſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lu. 10.37</note> For his fellowes debt was but a ſmall ſumme, an hundred pence; and ought therefore the rather to mooue him to haue béene pittifull, but he is neuer the better.</p>
            <p>Euen as many now adayes, to whom the Lord hath ſhewed great mercy in giuing them great aboundance, and much enereaſe, <hi>frumenti, vini, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> olei,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 4.8</note> 
               <hi>or corne, wine, and oyle,</hi> as the Prophet ſaith: Yea, <hi>the wicked liue and waxe old, and growe in wealth,<note place="margin">Iob. 21.7 8. &amp;c.</note> their ſeede is eſtabliſhed in their fight, their houſes are peaceable without feare, the rodde of GOD is not vpon them, their Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke gendreth, their Cowe Calueth, and faileth not, their Children daunce
<pb facs="tcp:21861:23"/>and make merry with Tabret, Harpe, and Organs,<note place="margin">Amos. 6.4</note> and ſpend their dayes in wealth, Lying downe vpon their beds, eating fatt Calues and Lambes, ſinging to the Violl, and drinking wine in bowles, but no man is ſory for the affliction of <hi>Ioſeph.</hi>
               </hi> Nay as the Apoſtle ſaith, more then this, and farre beyond the cruelty of this man, towards his fellow ſeruant, many riche couetous wretches appreſſe the <hi>poore by tyrannie,<note place="margin">Iam 2.6</note> drawing them before the Iudgment ſeate,</hi> clapping them vp in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, taking all their liuing and mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance from them, which this euill ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant did not: and ſo voide of all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion and mercy, kéepe their poore neighbours there, till gentle death baile them out of their bloudie fingers, <hi>thus reproching him that made them,<note place="margin">Pro. 14.31 Iam. 2.7.</note> and blaſpheming the worthy name after which they are named.</hi> Therefore why ſhould they be honored, that thus diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor God, but <hi>euen weepe and howle for the miſeries that ſhall come vpon them,<note place="margin">&amp; 5.1.2.3</note> becauſe their riches are corrupt, and their garments Moth-eaten, their gold and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer canckred, and the ruſt thereof ſhall be
<pb facs="tcp:21861:23"/>a witneſſe againſt them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 6.16</note> 
               <hi>and eate their fleſh as it were fire, thus they ſhall haue their rewarde:</hi> ſo that as the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher ſaith; <hi>the ſoule is loſt,<note place="margin">Plato.</note> that deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in couetouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus we ſée how he dealt with <hi>his fellow ſeruant.</hi> Now a word or two, how he was dealt with all, for his barbarous cruelty towards his fellow ſeruant.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt his other fellow ſeruants were greatly mooued, at his vnmercifull dealings, inſomuch that they accuſe him to their maiſter, for indéed man (who is the principall worke of nature,<note place="margin">Pſa. 8.5</note> 
               <hi>crowned with glory and worſhip,</hi> and for whoſe ſake the <hi>very Angels are ſent to miniſter,<note place="margin">Heb. 1.14</note> eſpecially for ſuch as ſhall receiue the inheritance of ſaluation,</hi>) by nature lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth mercie: knowing there is no man but ſhall haue néede of mercy, as the ſame Apoſtle affirmeth, <hi>Omnes ſunt pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catores &amp; deficiuntur gratià Dei:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 3.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pſa. 14. &amp; 69.30. &amp; 70.5. Iam. 1.19</note> 
               <hi>All are ſinners and ſtand in need of Gods grace,</hi> as the Prophet) plainelye prooueth throughout the Pſalme. But God (our heauenly Father the Fountaine of all mercy, <hi>who is ſlowe to wrath,</hi> as the
<pb facs="tcp:21861:24"/>Apoſtle ſaith,) hateth all crueltie, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially this cruelty, which the very Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then (which neuer knew God nor his lawes,) could not endure, <hi>viz. poutem frangere quem ipſe tranſiſti, <hi>to breake and pull vp the bridge after himſelfe hath eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped,</hi>
               </hi> that no man elſe may eſcape but bée drowned, this is a great and a moſt ſanadge cruelty.</p>
            <p>Now his fellow ſeruants bring in their verdict againſt him for his diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie and monſtrous inhumanity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Then commeth in the ſecond point. <hi>viz.</hi> that the King is altered, and his minde cleane changed, for whereas before there was no ſigne of anger at all in him, but extended his great fauour towards him, in forgiuing him the debt, <hi>verſe. 27.</hi> now his mercye is turned into méere and ſeueare Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and his good-will into extreame wrath.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, whereas before he vſed no hard ſpéeches, nor any vnkind words vnto him, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> now he calleth him <hi>lewd and euill ſeruant, verſ. 32.</hi> wherein wee are to take héede how we incurre the Lords
<pb facs="tcp:21861:24"/>diſpleaſure, by any hard and cruell dealings towards our debtors or poore brethren.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.8</note> For euen as <hi>mercy couereth a multitude of ſinnes,</hi> euen ſo cruelty in not hearing their complaints, and not <hi>ſhewing mercy,</hi> incurreth the wrath of God:<note place="margin">1. The. 4.6 Deu. 16.19</note> 
               <hi>For hee ſhall crie himſelfe and not be heard, for the Lord is the auenger of all ſuch things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A good <hi>Caueat</hi> for Magiſtrates, and all ſuch as to whom the hearing and deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of poore oppreſſed mens cauſes doth appertaine, that they be neither partiall on the one ſide, nor the other, for rewards, pitty, feare, or any fauour, but <hi>Iudge the people with righteous iudgement:</hi> whereby the integritie of ancient Juſtice may be preſerued, and not like vnto certaine <hi>Lacedemonian Ephori,</hi> tetchleſſe Magiſtrates, that heard mens cauſes (as they ſay) with their harueſt eares, nor yet like <hi>Adria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> the Emperor, that caſt all the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications of his poore petitioners, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the water before their faces, but euen like the LORD himſelfe, the Iudge of all Iudges, this King, <hi>who
<pb facs="tcp:21861:25"/>accepteth the riche and poore all alike,<note place="margin">De. 10.17 Iob. 34.19</note> yea the Prince,</hi> no more then the pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, but <hi>hearkneth and heareth,<note place="margin">Mal. 3.16 Exo. 22.23 Eccle. 35.</note> yea,</hi> and <hi>reuengeth the wrongs done vnto the poore oppreſſed, bee they widdowes, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe, friendleſſe, or comfortleſſe, or any wayes diſtreſſed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 21.12.13.</note> which <hi>is more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to him then ſacrifice:</hi> and <hi>to do iuſtice betimes in the morning,<note place="margin">Pro. 21.3</note> 
                  <hi>viz.</hi>
               </hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any delay, which is the bane of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a poore mans cauſe, and the very ſhipwrack of him and his:<note place="margin">Wiſd. 6</note> for a great <hi>Iudgement ſhall they haue that beare rule ouer the people.</hi> Therefore <hi>deliuer the oppreſſed,<note place="margin">Ier. 21.12</note> out of the hands of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſor, leaſt the wrath of the Lord goe out like fire, and burne, that none can quench it, becauſe of ſinne and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> Fourthly, the iuſt iudgment of the King, vpon him for his cruelty towards his fellow ſeruant, for whereas before hee condemned him to bee ſolde onely, now hee condemneth him to be tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Now wee ſée that his iudgment is more ſeuere, then it was before, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we haue to learne, that God ſtandeth
<pb facs="tcp:21861:25"/>otherwiſe affected to a mallicious and mercileſſe ſinner, then to one that is but a bare ſinner, ſuch an one as falleth through weakneſſe and imperfection, for there is great difference betwixt the infirmities of Gods children, and the vnregenerat, for although the godly fall through infirmity,<note place="margin">Ecc. 19.16</note> yet they ſtriue againſt ſinne before they commit it, and are ſorrowfull for it afterwards, but the wicked neither labour by prayer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, neither are they grieued nor humbled afterwards:<note place="margin">Pro. 2.14</note> but as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>potius letantur cum male fecerint, et exultent in rebus peſſimis,<note place="margin">&amp; 24.16</note> 
                  <hi>they are glad when they haue done euill, and reioyce in things moſt wicked:</hi> pius labitur in domo, ſed non a domo, <hi>the godly ſlip and fall in the houſe, but not out of it;</hi>
               </hi> they riſe againe, but the wicked play as one that breaketh his neck, and neuer riſeth againe: the godly haue the <hi>reliques of ſinne</hi> remaining in them, but not <hi>the kingdome of Sathan</hi> reigning in them,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> but as for malicious ſinners; the world was neuer ſo peſtred with them,<note place="margin">Mallicious ſinners.</note> as it is now a dayes, againſt whom the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
<pb facs="tcp:21861:26"/>prayeth with imprecations, that the Lord will not bee mercifull vnto them, becauſe <hi>they ſinne of malicious wickedneſſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 59.5 &amp; 1.1.</note> ſuch are all <hi>that ſitte in the ſeate of the ſcornefull,</hi> that ſnuffe and puffe when they are told of their ſinnes, which is a token of reprobation, and contrary wiſe a ſigne of the child of God, when we can ſay with <hi>Dauid, <hi>percutiat me iuſtus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">&amp; 141.5</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; redarguat,</hi> let the godly ſmite me friendly and reprooue me,</hi> as <hi>Nathan</hi> reprooued him for <hi>Vrias</hi> wife,<note place="margin">1. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 12.7</note> which hee, (although a King) tooke very patiently and cryed <hi>peccaui:</hi> a good example for all men. Malicious ſinners, alſo are all <hi>Ahabs</hi> and <hi>Iezabels</hi> and <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zars,</hi> ſuch couerous cormorant, Cater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pillers and Church-robbers, as will neither ſuffer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oore <hi>Naboth</hi> to enioy his Wineyard, nor the Miniſter his Tithes quietly, whereby Gods people are not onely robbed of both temporall and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall foode, life and ſoule, but alſo God of his honor, and glory. For take away liuing and maintenance, take away both life and learning, take away learning, and take away preaching: and take
<pb facs="tcp:21861:26"/>away preaching and then what follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, but all diſorder and confuſion, for <hi>where there is no viſion, <hi>viz.</hi> preaching,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 29.18</note> 
               <hi>there the people periſh,</hi> by famine the people faint and dye:<note place="margin">Amo. 8 11</note> but no famine ſo gréenous, as that <hi>of the word of God,</hi> which bréedeth and bringeth the lean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, faintneſſe, and famiſhment of the ſoule.<note place="margin">Pſa. 106.15</note> Yet ſuch <hi>fellow ſeruants</hi> this world is full of, who although they haue no Réede, neither of <hi>Naboths</hi> Wineyard, nor Church-liuings, appointed <hi>ad pios vſus, <hi>to godly purpoſes,</hi>
               </hi> yet they will throttle their fellow ſeruants for them: and ſuch malicious ſinners are alſo all that know a matter to bee naught, and yet will take part with it, and mony to defend it, as many of our lewd, vnconſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cionable Atturneſs, and pelting petti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foggers doe, and ſo bee they that take money, and neuer ſpeake a word in a mans cauſe, and ſuch be thoſe that <hi>iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie rhe wicked and condemne the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent,</hi> either for feare, fauour,<note place="margin">Pro. 18.5. &amp; 17.15.</note> bribes or rewards, which as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith <hi>is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homination vnto the Lord,</hi> with many more, <hi>as keepers backe of the hyrelings
<pb facs="tcp:21861:27"/>wages,</hi> and <hi>common blaſphemers:</hi> and ſuch a mallicious ſinner was this <hi>euill ſeruant,</hi> in dealing ſo cruelly with his fellow; and yet not ſo cruell as many now adayes, which caſt their poore bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in priſon without any iuſt cauſe, taking all their liuing from them: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it may be ſaid vnto ſuch kinde of fellowes, as that Father ſaith, <hi>Si in ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem mittendus eſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. Mat. 3.10</note> 
               <hi>quia ſua non dedit, vbi put as mittendus, qui aliena rapit, <hi>if he ſhall be caſt into the fire, that hath not giuen of his owne vnto the poore? whether ſhall h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> bee caſt that taketh theirs from them?</hi>
               </hi> if there be an <hi>ite malidicti, <hi>a goe yee curſed,</hi>
               </hi> for them that doe not viſit and comfort thoſe that are in priſon, without ſuccour and reliefe: what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth for them that voyde of all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion caſt them into priſon, there kéep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them continually, without conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, feare of God, or ſhame of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world. Our inferiors (ſaith one Father) do ſo looke for our mercy,<note place="margin">Greg. Naz. de pauper.</note> as wee at time of néede doe looke for Gods mercy. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if a ſinner that hath obtained mercy at Gods hands, many &amp; ſundry wayes,
<pb facs="tcp:21861:27"/>both in temporall and ſpirituall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, in ſo much that hee wanteth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that his heart can deſire, and then be mercileſſe vnto his brother, that hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly intreateth him to forbeare him a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and will not forgiue him a light of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, but beyond all Chriſtianitie, will <hi>take him by the throate, verſ. 28.</hi> vexe and trouble him, laye friuolous actions vpon him, caſt him in priſon, and ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doo him, his poore wife and children, as the manner of many mercileſſe men is now adayes, whereby they can neither doe their dutie to God nor man, with any quiet conſcience in their place and vocation, God will he wrathfully diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed, and <hi>reuenge the ſame,<note place="margin">Exod. 22 23.1, Theſ. 4.6</note> they ſhall periſh with the ſword, their wiues ſhalbe widowes, and their children fatherleſſe,</hi> and as the Prophet ſaith; <hi>their ſworde ſhall goe through their owne throate,<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.14 15</note> and all for caſting downe the poore and needie.</hi> Loe thus will God plague all cruell and couetous oppreſſors. This made. <hi>Plato</hi> ſay,<note place="margin">Plato.</note> that where there are beggers in a towne, there are théeues and Church-robbers. Now therefore
<pb facs="tcp:21861:28"/>if wee, that beare the name of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, acknowledging the poore our deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and néedy brethren, to be the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> are not aſhamed to ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet and feaſt, and let them ſtatue in the ſtréetes, nay vexe and trouble, whip, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, and caſt them in priſon, and there to let them pine and periſh: ſhall not the very Heathen, that neuer heard of God, riſe vp in iudgement at the laſt day, before that iuſt Iudge, to accuſe and condemne vs as théeues, Church-robbers, and murderers, but eſpecially ſuch as maintaine their vaine delights and filthy pleaſures, with the goods of the poore, and patrimonie of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards whome the diſtribution of our owne wealth ought to be exionded, both by the law of God and man; ſhall not our owne conſciences alſo accuſe vs? and be as <hi>mille teſtes, <hi>a thouſand witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes againſt vs?</hi>
               </hi> when it ſhall be ſayd vnto vs,<note place="margin">Luc. 16.2</note> 
               <hi>redde rationem, <hi>come giue an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt?</hi>
               </hi> for our ſelues, <hi>Adam? <hi>vbi es?</hi> where art thou?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cen 3.9.</note> and how haſt thou wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in my commandements? an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt for our bodyes, <hi>if they haue beene
<pb facs="tcp:21861:28"/>kept as the temples of the holy Ghoſt?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.19.</note> an accompt of our ſoules,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.25 Reu. 22.12 Mat. 12.36 Wiſd. 1.9</note> 
               <hi>if they bee fit to appeare in the ſight and preſence of the great ſheepheard,</hi> an accompt <hi>for our workes, words, and thoughts?</hi> and alſo an accompt how we haue vſed our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren? <hi>Cain, <hi>vbi est frater tuus</hi> Abel?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 4.9</note> 
               <hi>where is thy brother?</hi> if there be <hi>à diſcite ex me, <hi>learne of me,</hi>
               </hi> by the riche glutton, <hi>that fared diliciouſlie euery day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lu. 16.25</note> neglec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the miſerable eſtate of poore <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus:</hi> what are all oppreſſors of their poore brethren to expect at the dreadfull day of iudgement, but euen with moſt ſorrowfull ſobbing ſighes, and mourne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full moanes, fall a wiſhing that they had neuer vſed ſuch hard dealings, and cruell oppreſſion towards their poore brethren and <hi>fellow ſeruants?</hi> but alas now it is too late.</p>
            <p>Therefore when a man hath had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe at Gods hands for his ſinnes, to forgiue our brother and fellow ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant in like ſort, is not a matter of guift but of dutie, <hi>non opportuit? <hi>oughteſt thou not? verſ. 33.</hi>
               </hi> Yes ſurely, hauing recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued mercy, thou art bound to ſhew
<pb facs="tcp:21861:29"/>mercy: if thou haue ten thouſand talents forgiuen thée, oughteſt not thou to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue an hundred pence?<note place="margin">Couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and Crueltie alwayes compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> yes certainly, but here wee may plainly ſée, that coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, and crueltie, are alwayes companions, for if the King that cannot offend thée, (but thou him) ſhall forgive thée? oughteſt not thou to forgiue thy fellow ſeruant, whom thou maiſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend? and ſo ſtand in néede of his mercy?</p>
            <p>In as much therefore as thou haſt not done as thou oughteſt to haue done, <hi>Ex are tuo te iudico.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lu. 19.22</note> 
               <hi>I iudge thee out of thineowne mouth:</hi> for as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>hee that findeth friendſhip ought to ſhew himſelfe friendly againe towards others.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 18.24</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now for the concluſion, the laſt <hi>verſe 35.</hi> as I ſayd is the key for the opening of this parable, and it lays vs all in this dutie.</p>
            <p>God is our King, and we his ſubiects, we become his debtors by our ſinnes, and as we looke to haue forgiueneſſe at his hands, ſo wee muſt forgiue one an other. For as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>this was
<pb facs="tcp:21861:29"/>not written for <hi>Abraham</hi> onely:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 4.23</note> 
               <hi>that hee was iuſtified,</hi> but alſo for all the faithfull: ſo likewiſe this parable, we muſt apply vnto our ſelues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the point of forgiuing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> Firſt wee muſt know it is <hi>ſimile regi,</hi> like a King,<note place="margin">Pro. 20.21</note> God our heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and King commandeth this dutie, as an honorable thing, that we be ready to forgiue, as wee would haue GOD forgiue vs, and doth accept it as done vnto himſelfe,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.40</note> 
               <hi>whatſoeuer wee doe vnto his poore members, whom he calleth his little ones, and his brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Secondly, as I forgaue you, is a matter of dutie and equitie, and not of equitie onely, but alſo of Iuſtice, <hi>non oportuit? <hi>oughteſt thou not?</hi>
               </hi> ſéeing thou haſt receiued mercy? yes verily, thou art bound to ſhew mercy.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Thirdly, in reſpect of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, for hee that ſheweth mercy ſhall be rewarded with mercy. Yea in the kingdome of heauen, as our Sauiour
<pb facs="tcp:21861:30"/>ſaith:<note place="margin">Mat. 9.41.</note> 
               <hi>For God is not vnrighteous, that hee will forget your workes of mercy, therefore bee mercifull after they power.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 6.10 Tob 4.8 Luc. 6.13</note> for in ſo dooing, thou ſhalt not onely ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine forbearance, but alſo an acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of thy debt.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4</hi> Fourthly, for the puniſhment of beeing mercileſſe, for whereas before God was milde,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> hee will bee wrothe, whereas before hee was condemned to be ſolde onely, now hée ſhall bee grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly tormented, vntill hee haue the whole due, <hi>verſe. 34.</hi> a moſt heauſe and<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> horrible ſentence for mercileſſe men to thinke vpon.</p>
            <p>The Prophet,<note place="margin">Pſ. 118.12</note> 
               <hi>his enemies ſhall come about him like Bees, not waſpes,</hi> becauſe hes gathered hony from them: ſo there is profit to bée reaped from our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, but the profit that we ſhall reape by this Chriſtian charitie, is, wee ſhall (as it were) make God bound vnto vs, by forgiuing.</p>
            <p>It is that which ſome note vpon the words of the Pſalmiſt, where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſaith, <hi>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mber mee according to thy word,<note place="margin">Pſ. 119.49</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21861:30"/>wherein thou haſt cauſed mee to put my truſt,</hi> that is; wee conuent thée O Lord vpon thy promiſe, to forgiue vs our treſpaſſes, becauſe wee haue forgiuen our brethren their offences.</p>
            <p>Now therefore, if the reward will not ſerue to ſtirre vs vp vnto this dutie of mercy towards our poore brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren? then the puniſhment muſt, which neuer faileth, <hi>viz. <hi>ſic faciat vobis;</hi> ſo hee ſhall doe vnto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if ſome, perhaps vnderſtand it not, <hi>quando adductus erit,</hi> when hee ſhall be brought, hee ſhall vnderſtand, that hee hath not onely loſt the reward, but alſo incurred the puniſhment, from the which the Lord and Father of all mercy, vouchſafe to deliuer vs, for his ſonne <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> his ſake, our onely Sauiour and redéemer. To whom with the holy Ghoſt, thrée perſons and one God, be all powre and glory, praiſe and dominion, now and for euer, world without end.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
